Have you ever wondered
if there are more natural ways
to lower your high blood pressure,
guard against Alzheimer's,
lose weight, and feel better?
Well, it turns out there is!
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today, we look at different ways
to get the benefits of GLP-1,
with natural Ozempic alternatives.
I’ve talked about the upsides
of pharmacologically boosting
GLP-1 activity
in terms of weight loss,
given the ravages of obesity,
and I’ve also discussed
its downsides,
including common
gastrointestinal reactions
and muscle loss,
as well as the rarer
and more speculative
side effects
such as thyroid cancer,
pancreatitis,
and pancreatic cancer.
And I’ve summarized
the cost-benefit trade-off,
detailing for whom the benefits
may far outweigh the risks,
at least in the short term.
But is there any way
to get the benefits of GLP-1
without the risks,
by boosting it naturally
with diet and lifestyle changes?
Well, there’s exercise.
It appears
to acutely increase GLP-1.
There have been five studies
of exercise and GLP-1,
and four out of five of them
found higher concentrations
of total GLP-1
after High Intensity
Interval Training
and Sprint Interval Training
as well as Moderate Intensity
Continuous Training,
with no apparent difference
between High Intensity Interval
and Moderate Intensity
Continuous.
Compared to control groups
where the study subjects
didn’t exercise at all,
both types of physical activity
(High Intensity Interval and
Moderate Intensity Continuous)
induced significantly higher
GLP-1 concentrations
immediately after exercise,
and 30-90 minutes later.
Unfortunately, there appeared
to be publication bias,
meaning some trials
that failed to show an effect
may have been quietly shelved,
thereby skewing the results.
But what’s the downside
of exercising?
The evidence is overwhelming
that nearly everyone
can benefit
from becoming
more physically active.
What about diet?
There are a variety
of natural products,
foods, beverages, and spices,
that have been shown to boost
our own natural GLP-1 levels.
But can endogenous GLP-1,
meaning GLP-1
from inside the body,
work as an alternative
to the drugs that mimic GLP-1,
like Ozempic?
If you haven’t yet,
I recommend watching
or re-watching my video
about what GLP-1 is
and how it works,
to best fully grasp
the issue at hand.
Our natural GLP-1 levels
rise and fall
in response to meal ingestion.
When we take
these drugs, though,
levels in our blood remain
relatively constant, and high.
But "high" here
is a bit of an understatement.
The total concentration
of these GLP-1 lookalike drugs
in our bloodstream
is typically around
20-30 nanomoles per liter.
Okay, here’s how much GLP-1
rises naturally
in our bloodstream
in the two hours
after we eat a meal,
up to maybe 20 or 30 picomoles.
"Nano-" means billionth;
"pico-" means trillionth.
So, at this scale,
drug levels are up
to like 25,000.
How could
boosting natural levels
even come close?
Well, part of the discrepancy
may be an artifact
of taking blood
from people’s veins
to do blood tests.
Since natural GLP-1
is rapidly deactivated
by an enzyme in our blood,
by the time GLP-1
is secreted by our gut,
makes it through our liver,
heart, and lungs,
then out into our arteries,
only to later reach the veins
where the lab tech
is pulling out blood,
the levels we see are lower
than the arterial levels
that GLP-1 receptors
are exposed to
throughout our body,
though only
by a relatively small amount.
But how do drugs like Ozempic
sit around in the body
for weeks instead of minutes?
They are chemically modified
to stick to the most abundant
protein in our blood.
So, even though the total
drug level in our blood
is up in the nanomolar range,
it’s so tightly bound to protein
that the active level
in our blood
that’s free to actually interact
with tissue receptors
is like a hundred times smaller,
at least down
in the picomolar range.
Thus, although at first glance,
it appears
that plasma drug levels
are extremely high,
they actually may be closer
to those of natural GLP-1 levels
after strong stimulation.
But still, there seems
to be a huge discrepancy.
It’s GLP-1 activation
in the brain
that appears to account for
the regulation of food intake,
but it isn’t currently clear
how this might be related
to GLP-1 in the blood.
The primary source
of GLP-1 secretion
in the body is the gut.
So, wouldn’t it get eaten up
by enzymes in the blood
before much of it
even made it into the brain?
It can cross
the blood-brain barrier,
but is enough
really getting up there?
Well, GLP-1 is also produced
by nerves
in the brainstem itself,
and a large body of evidence
points to
the appetite-reducing effects
of GLP-1 mimicking drugs,
like Ozempic,
being mediated by
these brain GLP-1 receptors.
So, how could
natural blood levels,
expected after
dietary interventions,
aiming to increase
the secretion of gut GLP-1
still have
clinically relevant effects?
Yes, the GLP-1 released
from our intestinal cells
is rapidly degraded,
leading to low systemic levels,
but its effects
appear to be mediated
by vagus nerve stimulation.
The vagus nerve
connects the gut
straight up
into the brainstem,
so it’s directly wired
to the brain
and doesn’t have to rely
on blood transport.
But wait, there are GLP-1
receptors on the pancreas,
the kidneys,
the liver, and the heart.
Why would the body
have GLP-1 receptors
on our peripheral organs,
if the hormone acts mainly
through the vagus nerve?
It’s possible
that strong stimuli
can boost levels
high enough in the blood
to activate
these peripheral receptors.
So, perhaps,
the way GLP-1 normally works
is that we eat a meal,
and GLP-1 sends
the appetite reducing signal
to our brain directly
through the vagus nerve,
and then, our brain
relays the messages
to the relevant systems
throughout the body.
Injecting people
with high levels
of a GLP-1-mimicking drug,
like Ozempic,
means it can circulate
directly through the bloodstream
to all these organs,
including the brain,
and a strong
dietary GLP-1 stimulus
might be able to do both.
But you can’t really know
whether natural,
physiological levels of GLP-1
can suppress appetite,
until you...
put it to the test.
When different levels of GLP-1
are dripped
straight into people’s veins,
you can see
a dose-dependent reduction
in both hunger and food intake.
Okay, but effective doses
used in infusion studies
quadrupled baseline levels
or more,
whereas the blood levels
increased by
GLP-1-boosting foods
tended to only double
baseline levels.
So, while high-dose
GLP-1 infusion
drives a clear change
in hunger and eating behaviors,
is it possible
that inducing GLP-1 secretion
through diet may not?
Well, remember how food
naturally only boosts
blood levels up around 20?
It turns out you can get
a significant drop
in food intake
up to 30-35% less
of an all-you-can-eat meal
simply by getting your GLP-1
levels up to 10 or 15,
or even just 5!
That is well within
doable dietary ranges.
So, while low natural levels
might appear to have
little effect at first glance,
a slight increase in levels
by dietary manipulation
of GLP-1 secretion
could be sufficient
to have clinical relevance.
Thus, we don’t have to strive
for levels comparable to those
obtained using drugs.
And, of course,
this makes sense, right?
Why would our body
naturally produce
an appetite-suppressing hormone
in response to food,
if it didn’t end up
suppressing our appetite?
This review on
boosting the hormone GLP-1
by natural products
concluded there are
compelling studies
that suggest that
the berberine in barberries,
quercetin in capers,
red onions, and buckwheat,
ginseng, ginger root, gardenia,
green tea,
wheat fiber, soybeans,
curcumin in turmeric, cinnamon,
and resveratrol in grapes,
each have potent effects
on GLP-1 activity.
The hope is that
increasing the release
of our own GLP-1 hormone
by eating specific foods
could have similar benefits
to GLP-1-mimicking drugs,
without their potentially
disabling side effects.
But any time a review
makes a statement of fact,
like, "Potent effects
on GLP-1 activity,"
it’s always important
to dig up the original studies,
the so-called
"primary literature."
For example,
here’s the section on soy:
researchers demonstrated
that soybeans
can normalize blood sugars
by inducing GLP-1 secretion,
dietary consumption
of soybean protein
induces GLP-1
and, moreover,
soybean protein increases
GLP-1 expression and secretion.
"This combined evidence
strongly suggests
that soybean protein
exerts modulatory effects
on GLP-1 secretion."
Sounds great!
But if you pull
these three sources,
that was based on studies
on mice, rats,
and in Petri dishes.
Gardenia-derived products
also purportedly
potentiate GLP-1 secretion
based on cells and rodents,
but, when actually tested
in humans,
those in the gardenia group
actually showed
a decrease in GLP-1.
Evidence also suggests ginseng
improves GLP-1 secretion,
but again, that’s just evidence
from rats and test tubes.
What about that
red wine compound, resveratrol?
Works in diabetic rats,
but not in diabetic humans.
Green tea is said to increase
GLP-1 levels in actual patients,
actual human patients!
But, in fact,
the increase over placebo
did not reach
statistical significance.
Olive oil is said to induce
higher GLP-1 concentrations
than butter,
but the study that was cited,
this one,
actually showed
no significant difference.
This was
on healthy subjects, though;
a similar study
on those with diabetes
did show a larger
GLP-1 response,
though only by about 15 percent.
Avocados have lots
of monounsaturated fats, too.
And online,
you’ll find so-called experts
who claim that
eating avocados can be,
"as effective as getting
weight-loss injections,"
a food that works
"just like the miracle
weight-loss jab Ozempic,"
and that’s from a nutritionist!
"Guaca-mo-zempic"
may work if you’re a rat,
but in humans,
GLP-1 was found to be
significantly lower
in the avocado-added meal.
Speaking of online speculation,
what do we know about berberine,
the supplement dubbed
"Nature’s Ozempic,"
a component of barberries,
a dried fruit
I’ve previously profiled
as a treatment for acne?
Well, berberine
boosts GLP-1 secretion
in rats and Petri dishes,
but there haven’t been any
GLP-1 studies on humans yet.
What we care about, though,
is weight loss,
and there have been
a bunch of studies
on the effects
of berberine and barberries
on body weight.
No effect was found,
either for berberine supplements
or barberries themselves.
This is all very disappointing.
Something in the spice
"fenugreek"
seemed to boost GLP-1 signaling
in a test tube,
but there are no human studies,
and it didn’t even work in mice.
So, fenugreek flopped,
but there are some spices
that can legitimately
boost GLP-1 in humans.
If you have people
eat the same meal,
but chew each bite
either 15 times or 40 times,
the blood levels
of the appetite-suppressing
hormone GLP-1
in the blood stream
are higher
after 40 chews than 15,
and those who chewed 40 times
ended up consuming
about 75 fewer calories
than the 15-time chewers.
The researchers suggest
that chewing more
may help people
keep their weight down.
Okay, but who wants to sit there
and count how many times
they chew?
What if you just eat
chewier foods?
What if you have people
eat shredded cabbage,
which requires a lot of chewing,
or the same amount
of pureed cabbage;
same food, but requiring
different amounts of chewing?
GLP-1 blood levels were higher
in the shredded cabbage
chewing group
than the pureed cabbage
non-chewing one,
at 45, 60, and 90 minutes,
at least initially.
The researchers were careful
to make sure
both groups ate
at the same rate,
because eating
even the same food more slowly
can result in a greater
GLP-1 response.
Researchers had people
eat the same amount of ice cream
over a period of either
five minutes or 30 minutes,
and those who ate
the exact same amount
of the same food more slowly
experienced a significant boost
in GLP-1 levels in their blood
for hours after the meal,
about a 30 percent bump overall.
On average, the participants
were overweight,
but a lot slimmer
than your average American.
What about essentially
re-doing the same study,
but with obese individuals
who could really use
the extra GLP-1 boost?
And here we go.
The researchers found
disparate results
when they tested
obese adolescents
versus obese adults.
With the obese teens,
researchers saw the same outcome
as they did with
the overweight adults;
a significantly higher
GLP-1 response
after slower eating.
But the rate of eating
didn’t seem to matter
in obese adults.
Same thing with satiety.
Obese adolescents felt fuller,
more satiated for longer
when eating more slowly,
but speed of eating
didn’t seem to matter
in the adults with obesity.
But, at least for some,
more chewing
and eating more slowly
may raise GLP-1 levels,
no matter what’s consumed.
But are there certain foods
that specifically boost GLP-1?
There are a few
spices that might.
Volunteers were served
rice with vegetable curry
made with three different
doses of spices.
The bland control meal
had no spices at all,
just tomato puree with eggplant.
The low-spice meal added
a tablespoon of curry spices,
plus onions, garlic, and ginger.
And the third variation,
the high-spice curry,
had double the spices,
two tablespoons.
The spices were turmeric,
coriander seeds, cumin seeds,
dried Indian gooseberry powder--
also known as amla--
cayenne pepper,
cinnamon, and cloves
mixed in the ratio of eight
to four to four to four,
to two to one to one,
respectively.
And the average bump
in GLP-1 blood concentration
for those eating
both the low-spice
and high-spice meals
were 17 and 32 percent higher,
compared to the bland
control meal without the spices.
About the same calories
and macronutrients,
but the spicier meals
raised GLP-1 levels higher.
But which spice was it?
Ginger compounds boosts
GLP-1 in mice but not rats,
and in humans, we appeared
to react more like the rats:
no effect.
For many of the other spices,
there isn’t even in vitro data,
but rather only in silico,
meaning just some kind
of computer modeling
that didn’t actually test
anything in a biological system.
But we do have data on curcumin,
the yellow compound
found in the spice turmeric.
This study used
180 milligrams of curcumin,
which is the amount found in
a single teaspoon of turmeric.
The researchers also tested
fish oil supplements,
but while the fish oil failed,
the curcumin
reduced the blood sugar spike
after a meal,
which is something both
GLP-1 and GLP-1 drugs can do,
though GLP-1 levels
weren’t directly measured.
The researchers suggest
it may be a GLP-1 effect,
since curcumin
stimulates GLP-1 in rodents,
as well as cells
in a Petri dish,
but there hasn’t been
a human study until now.
Six months
of curcumin supplementation
led to a quadrupling
of GLP-1 levels,
compared to placebo.
Okay, so, turmeric may help.
What about cinnamon?
Scandinavian researchers
gave people rice pudding
with and without
one or three grams of cinnamon,
which is about
a third of a teaspoon,
or a full teaspoon.
And those getting
the full teaspoon of cinnamon
more than doubled
the GLP-1 bump-from-baseline
compared to the control pudding
without the cinnamon.
So, that’s another spice
that may work,
though people didn’t report
feeling any more satiated
eating the cinnamon-y pudding
compared to plain.
And finally, the third spice
to boost GLP-1 in humans?
Cayenne pepper.
What happened
when a half a teaspoon
of cayenne pepper
was added to a meal?
Over a short period of time--
15 minutes--
a single spicy meal
significantly increased
blood levels of GLP-1.
Though,
like in the cinnamon study,
this did not appear to translate
into them feeling any fuller,
but the researcher
didn’t measure
actual subsequent food intake.
Most of the poisons
used by humans
come from bitter plants.
For example,
strychnine and hemlock.
At the same time,
some of the most
popular beverages
in the world are bitter,
as are some
of the healthiest foods.
Bitter taste receptors
aren’t only on our tongue,
but throughout much
of our digestive tract,
on the very same cells
lining our gut that secrete
the appetite-suppressing
hormone, GLP-1.
And indeed,
a number of bitter compounds
have been shown
to potently stimulate
the release of hormones
like GLP-1
in Petri dishes and lab animals.
What about people?
And beer!
Bee is one of the most popular
bitter beverages,
thanks to hops.
Given that bitter herbs
have evidently been used
in times of scarcity
to reduce hunger,
researchers tested low and high
doses of hops extracts
on people undergoing
a 24-hour fast,
and found both doses seemed
to lower feelings of hunger
better than placebo.
Might that be a GLP-1 effect?
Let’s find out.
Taking a hops extract
before a meal,
in either immediate
or delayed-release capsules,
led to significantly more
GLP-1 release
than did a placebo.
And, more importantly,
when the study participants
were given
all-you-can-eat ham sandwiches
a few hours later,
they ate significantly less.
They didn’t feel significantly
less hungry or more full,
but, overall, still ate
about 200 calories less.
So, a bitter hop extract
significantly decreased
calorie intake,
while increasing
appetite-suppressing hormones,
like GLP-1.
These changes occurred
without the participants
feeling any different,
appetite-wise,
or liking the sandwiches
any less.
Now, the extract
did make them feel
nauseated, bloat-y, and barf-y,
but maybe
that’s just more evidence
it might be working
through GLP-1,
since those are
common side effects
of the GLP-1-mimicking drugs,
like Ozempic.
Well, wait,
no wonder they ate less,
but evidently, the degree
of gastrointestinal discomfort
did not correlate
with how much less they ate.
The main reason
I’d caution against hops
is because of a compound in hops
called 8-PN
that I’ve talked about before
in a two-part video series.
What about quinine,
perhaps the best-studied
bitter substance
in human history?
Extracted from the bark
of the cinchona tree,
quinine was not only
the first effective treatment
for malaria 400 years ago,
but, remarkably,
remains a common and effective
treatment to this day.
And give someone
275 milligrams of it,
and GLP-1 secretion
is stimulated.
Enough to actually reduce
appetite and body weight?
"Dietary quinine reduces
body weight and food intake,"
in rats.
What about in people?
"Intragastric
quinine administration
decreases hedonic eating,"
meaning eating for pleasure,
even if you aren’t
really hungry.
In this case,
a chocolate milkshake.
And if you’re thinking,
"Well, of course
they’d drink less milkshake
if they just had something
super bitter," but, no.
The quinine was administered
directly into their stomach
through a tube,
so it bypassed the bitter
receptors in their mouth.
There are still
those bitter receptors
in our gut, though,
that we aren’t even
consciously aware of.
The researchers
even did brain scans,
and concluded that
being unknowingly slipped
about 200 milligrams of quinine
not only affected
how much the study participants
felt like they wanted to eat,
but how much
they actually did eat,
by interfering
with reward brain circuits.
And you don’t have to go
lick some tree bark to get it.
It’s available
in every grocery store
in the form of tonic water.
A liter of tonic water has about
60 to 70 milligrams of quinine,
and bitter lemon,
another popular cocktail mixer,
has about half that.
But getting
200 milligrams of quinine
still would be like drinking
three quarts of tonic water.
Can we get away with less?
Yes.
In this study, people were given
just 18 milligrams of quinine,
or placebo,
and then, an hour later,
everyone was given
all-you-can-eat
ham and cheese sandwiches.
And caloric intake
was significantly lower
after the quinine than placebo
by about 14 percent.
So, drinking a third of a liter
of tonic water before a meal
could reduce your caloric intake
by 82 calories.
But a third of a liter
of tonic water
has more than
a hundred calories!
So, that wouldn’t
do you much good.
Tonic water is basically
quinine-spiked
carbonated sugar water.
Now, there are
sugar-free varieties,
or, you could go
straight to the source.
What if you got about
the same amount of quinine
in the form of powdered bark?
The effects of giving about
a third of a teaspoon a day
of powdered cinchona bark
on satiety, weight loss,
and body composition
in a population
of overweight adults.
Significantly more weight loss,
significantly more waist lost,
and even slimmer hips
in the bark group,
compared to placebo,
and the weight loss
was in fat mass,
with greater
lean mass preservation,
compared to placebo.
So, in humans,
quinine may boost GLP-1,
decrease hedonic hunger,
lower appetite,
decrease calorie intake,
and decrease body fat.
But there are "risks
for the consumption of quinine."
Quinine is a drug
and may in fact be among
the most common causes
of severe
drug-induced disorders.
Just the levels of quinine
found in tonic water
may cause potentially fatal
immunologically-mediated
hypersensitivity reactions,
basically
like allergic reactions,
where it interacts
with antibodies
to trigger autoimmune reactions
that can cause chills, fever,
a drop in blood pressure,
painful bluish discoloration
of the hands and feet,
and clotting
within your blood vessels.
It can also chew up
your red blood cells,
leading to anemia.
Chew up your platelets, leading
to bleeding and bruising.
And chew up
your white blood cells,
leading to immune dysfunction.
As well as
acute kidney injury,
the dissolution of your muscles,
liver toxicity, heart damage,
respiratory failure,
low blood sugars, blindness,
and toxic epidermal necrolysis,
which can manifest
as genital blistering,
sloughed penile erosion,
or an eroded scrotum.
Even minute exposure to quinine
in common beverages
can cause
severe adverse reactions
involving multiple
organ systems.
So, the "moral of the story"
is that a relaxing gin and tonic
may be the cause
of life-threatening disease.
Now, these are rare,
idiosyncratic reactions.
Just because peanuts
can be life-threatening
to someone with a peanut allergy
doesn’t mean everybody
needs to avoid peanuts.
But there are
non-hypersensitivity
adverse effects, too.
For example, when quinine
isn’t eroding scrotums,
it may still be shrinking them.
Researchers found quinine
so damaging
to the testicles of rats
that they suggested
that quinine should be explored
as male contraceptive.
Quinine is an extremely toxic
agent in overdose,
with vision loss
as a common outcome.
The reason people may have
quinine pills around their house
is that some people take them
for nocturnal leg cramps.
The U.S. Food and Drug
Administration concluded
that this was not safe;
so, it banned quinine’s use
for this purpose in both
over-the-counter preparations
and even in prescriptions,
after receiving
hundreds of reports
of serious adverse events
associated with quinine use,
including 93 deaths.
It’s still available
with a prescription
as a malaria drug, though,
which doctors were
prescribing for leg cramps,
skirting FDA recommendations,
but given its rare but serious
allergic-type reactions,
and risk of OD’ing
on quinine pills,
that’s probably not a good idea.
Thankfully,
following warnings by the FDA,
the use of quinine
for treatment of muscle cramps
has dramatically declined.
Of course, even though
the FDA banned it
from one aisle
of the drug store,
it still may be available
in another,
in the form of tonic water.
Yeah, but can
the lower levels of the drug
found in drinks
still cause problems?
Yes, an overdose
can leave you blind,
affecting not only the retina
in the back of your eye
but the iris in the front,
leading to oval pupils.
How bizarre is that?
Okay, okay,
but what if you don’t overdose?
Can quinine
still affect your vision?
Following the identification
by the Armed Forces
Institute of Pathology
of quinine in autopsy specimens
from military pilot fatalities,
researchers had volunteers
drink tonic water
for two weeks and were indeed
able to show some abnormalities.
Even transient blurring
of vision
can be disastrous if experienced
by anyone operating
heavy machinery at high speeds.
So, given the concern
that tonic water consumption
may have contributed
to aviation accidents,
the use of tonic water by pilots
is actually forbidden
three days before flying.
I didn’t know that.
So, how much is too much?
There was a case reported
of a 46-year-old man
with increasing
visual deterioration
and difficulty with
night driving over three months,
during which
he had been drinking
a gallon of tonic water a day.
Okay, so, a gallon
may be too much.
This person was drinking
a liter of tonic water
prior to the onset of his
"Quinine water-triggered
heart arrhythmia."
His doctors suggest the public
is simply unaware of the risks
associated with excessive
consumption of tonic water,
but how many people are drinking
almost a quart a day?
The "no-untoward-effect"
level in humans
has been estimated to be
52.5 mg of quinine a day,
which is about a two and a half
cups (590 ml) of tonic water.
Based on ototoxicity,
damage to our hearing,
maybe we shouldn’t
drink much more
than two cups (470 ml) a day,
but these levels are based on
trying to extrapolate
from animal models.
Since quinine was so commonly
prescribed to treat leg cramps,
can’t we just look at large
populations of people
and see if anything
bad happened?
Yes, indeed, we can,
and those prescribed quinine
had a 27 percent increased risk
of acute kidney injury,
which is not as bad as death:
"Association Between
Long-term Quinine Exposure
and All-Cause Mortality."
Following 175,000 people
for about six years,
researchers found
that those who were taking
about 200 mg of quinine a day
had a 25 percent
greater risk of dying.
Those on around 300 mg
had an 83 percent
greater risk of dying,
and those on 400 mg or more
appeared to double
their risk for death.
So, I would recommend
staying away from quinine.
Although the FDA has determined
that carbonated beverages
may safely contain up to 83 mg
of quinine per liter,
bottles of bubbly drinks usually
don’t say how much is in them,
and some popular brands
don’t even list it
as an ingredient at all.
How do you know if your drink
has quinine or not?
Hold it up to a black light,
and if it lights up
with an iridescent blue glow,
well, quinine
is the secret ingredient
for making
fluorescent Jell-O shots.
Visit nutritionfacts.org/audio to see
all of the podcast episodes
with descriptions that include
links to their associated videos.
Sources cited and other details are
available on each video's page.
Information about my books—
How Not to Die, How Not to Diet,
and How Not to Age—
is at nutritionfacts.org/books.
All proceeds from book
sales go to charity.
And sign up for our free newsletter
at nutritionfacts.org/subscribe
to stay updated on the latest
bite-sized videos and articles.
NutritionFacts.org is a
science-based non-profit,
and everything on
the website is free.
There are no ads, no corporate
sponsorships, no kickbacks.
Strictly non-commercial,
not selling anything.
I just put up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.
Thanks for listening.